"The Best Exercise Type
and Frequency for Bone Density"
When it comes to bone health,
it's use it or lose it.
Physical activity is considered
a widely accessible, low-cost,
and highly modifiable
contributor to bone health.
Exercise transmits forces
through the skeleton,
generating signals
that are detected
by your bone-building cells.
This is why the National
Osteoporosis Foundation,
International Osteoporosis
Foundation,
and other agencies recommend
weight-bearing exercise
for the prevention
of osteoporosis.
These include
high-impact exercises
such as jumping, aerobics,
and running,
as well as
lower impact exercises
like walking
and weight training
to create
those mechanical signals
that spark bone growth,
but sufficient intensity
and frequency are critical.
The large variation
in bone benefit
across different studies,
from negligible changes
to substantial improvements
in bone mineral density,
have been attributed
to the adequacy
of the exercise regime.
To improve measures
of bone strength
at the spine and hip,
the most effective
exercise training protocol
appears to be a combination
of progressive resistance
and impact training
at moderate to high intensity.
Low-intensity exercise does not
appear to be sufficient.
For example,
while regular walking
is often prescribed
to prevent osteoporosis,
it appears to offer
limited benefit
for bone loss prevention.
On its own, walking
has no significant effect
on bone mineral density
in the spine, wrist,
or overall skeleton,
but it has been shown
to significantly improve
hip bone density
in studies that have lasted
more than six months.
More effective would be
brisk walking,
walking with a weighted vest,
or combining walking
with more vigorous exercises
such as jogging, stepping,
or stair-climbing.
Non-impact activities
such as cycling or swimming
have been shown
to have little or no effect.
An elegant study to determine
the optimum frequency
of high-impact exercise
for bone health
involved hopping
on one randomly chosen foot,
with the person's other leg
acting as the control.
Women were randomized
to hop 50 times
on that one, same leg
either seven days a week,
four days a week,
two days a week,
or not at all for six months.
And the brief, daily hopping
increased hip bone density,
but less frequent hopping
was not effective.
The only group that built
significantly more bone
in their hip on the jumping
versus non-jumping side
within those six months
was the seven-day-a-week group.
If you jump 50 times
with about a 10-pound (4.5 kg)
weighted vest on, however,
you may be able to preserve
your hip bone density
with just three sessions a week
instead of every day.
Note, weight-bearing
impact exercise
may be contraindicated,
meaning not advisable,
in those
with severe osteoporosis
or recent history of fracture,
so make sure you check
with your medical professional
before you get going.